<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string-array name="titles">
        <item>History</item>
        <item>Front Hall</item>
        <item>Stair Landing</item>
        <item>Main Landing</item>
        <item>Front Bedroom</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="infos">
        <item><b><i>The Cannonball House was built in between 1853-1855</i></b> for Judge Asa Holt (pronounced “A-sa”) and his wife, Mary Palmer Holt. Judge Holt, a Probate Judge, also had 2 plantations in Louisville, Georgia, where he raised sheep as well as pigs, and also grew cash crops and had a couple of cotton gins. In the 1840s the Judge and Mary would move to Savannah, Ga where he would own a mercantile, as well as serve on the General Assembly.\n\n

              In March 1853, Judge Holt would purchase Lot 8, Square 69 on Mulberry Street, from Miss Sarah V. Green for $2,000. He would employ Elam Alexander to design and build a town home for him in the Greek Revival style. Taking 2 years to build, Elam Alexander would build a 2 bedroom “half house” for the Judge, with the total cost of the home being $7,000.\n\n

              Mary Palmer Holt would continue to live in the home until her death in January 1862, when she passed away from Dropsy of the Chest. The Judge would continue to live in the home by himself for 4 months before he would remarry, this time to Miss Nora Burke, of Athens, Georgia. Nora at the time was 30 years of age, the Judge was a  wise 71 years old.\n\n

              <b><i>In July, 1864,</i></b> during the War Between the States, Nora would be in Macon when General W. T. Sherman would send <b><i>General George Stoneman</i></b> to Macon. Macon was an industrial city for the Confederacy, and everything from cannons, cannonballs, medicine, uniforms, and dental equipment was made in Macon for the Confederate cause. General Stoneman was sent to Macon to destroy what he could of the city, as well as free the prisoners from Camp Orgethorpe, a Federal Officers prison on the outskirts of town, and then head to Andersonville, or Camp Sumter which is south of here, to free the prisoners from there as well.\n\n

              The Ocmulgee River, two blocks from here, would have flooded a few days before the Union army would come to Macon, ultimately keeping the troops across the River at the Dunlap’s Farm, today the Ocmulgee National Monument. In the morning hours of July 30, 1864, Stoneman would have his troops fire Hotchkiss Shells into Macon, destroying what he could of the City. One of those Hotchkiss Shells would hit  the sand sidewalk  in front of the Cannonball House, ricochet, hit the 3rd pillar in front of the front parlor, go through  the front wall in the Entrance Hall (where the mirror next to the door is today), and land though the floor, unexploded.\n\n
              Nora, returning from delivering linens to the Hospital on Mulberry Street, would have called Captain John W. Mallet, an ordnance Officer from the Confederate Laboratory.  He would remove the shell, and later write his superior officer that it was indeed a Hotchkiss Shell that would damage Judge Holt’s home.\n\n

              <b><i>In August of that year,</i></b> Nora would leave Macon to join Judge Holt at their plantation, or what she called her country home, in Louisville. They planned to be gone for 6 weeks, but they were still in Louisville in November 1864, when General Sherman’s troops would go through Louisville on their way to Savannah. Major damage was done to the plantation.  Ropes were cut from the wells, the livestock were all killed or stolen, and the troops had also heard rumors that Nora had packed all their gold in trunks and brought everything with her from Macon. Wanting that gold, they would take the 74 year old Judge Holt down to the Ogeechee Swamp (which was on his property) on the pretense of finding some syrup. They would ask where his gold was, the Judge would reply that he only had a few gold pieces as well as his watch, and they wouldn’t believe him. Hanging him to scare him, they would take him down and ask the question again. The 3rd time they hung him, he passed out, and when he revived he found himself lying next to a stream, with a soldier pouring water over his face and the sound of someone saying “We have carried this game to far.” He would be taken to the Main House where he would have Nora give them his pocket watch, and when she would ask why he would reply, “Because I am half dead.”\n\n

              Nora would nurse Judge Holt back to health, although he never would completely recover. They would return to Macon in March, 1865, and Judge Holt would continue to live in the Cannonball House until his death on May 26th 1872, when he would pass away at the age of 82.\n\n

              <b><i>Nora would re-marry in January, 1874</i></b> to Mr. Charles Canning, a widower 10 years her senior. He would move into the home with his 18 year old daughter, Lizzie. A few years later Mr. Canning’s older daughter, Kate Canning Martin, also a widow, would move into the home with her 3 children- Charles C. Martin, J. William Martin, and Katie J. Martin (Roberson).\n\n

              <b><i>Charles C. Martin</i></b> would continue to live in the home, and he married Miss Susie Postell in 1903. They would have one child, a daughter by the name of Elizabeth Martin, in 1904. Miss Elizabeth grew up in the home, and was the last family member to live in the house in 1962 when she was approached by the Sidney Lanier Chapter # 25, United Daughters of the Confederacy, of which she was a member. The UDC ladies wanted to purchase the home because it was the only home in Macon to have been directly affected by the War, use the home as a meeting house, and open the home for tours. It was perfect timing for Miss Elizabeth, because the City of Macon wanted to tear down the house and make it into a parking lot, all because she could not pay her taxes.\n\n

              Although Miss Elizabeth sold the house to the UDC ladies in 1962, they allowed her to continue to live in the home rent free until her death in 1971. The UDC ladies would keep the house until the 1990s, when they turned over the Cannonball House to the Friends of the Cannonball House, INC, a Non-Profit Organization.
</item>



        <item>The pictures on the table- The family picture was taken in the summer of 1885, after Kate C. Martin passed away at the age of 38. It shows Charles Canning, his wife Nora, daughter Lizzie, and Kate’s 3 children, Charlie, Willie, and Katie.\n\n

               The picture of the house was done before 1910, although Judge Holt would remember the house looking similar to this in the 1850s. The side room was added in the late 1850s as Judge Holt’s study. How you would enter into the room would have been under the staircase, where the restroom is today. In 1910, when the property was sold next door, the family moved the room to the other side of the house where it is the gift shop today.\n\n

               The Hotchkiss Shell by the front door in the case is the type of shell that came though the home in July 1864. When it was fired out of the cannon, flames would have gone through the three groves, where it would have lit a fuse. In the center of the shell would have been a place for more gunpowder, as well as shrapnel. The Cannonball on the right side of the case was thought for many years to be the original cannonball to come through the Cannonball House. It was in fact made in Macon, Georgia during the War Between the States.\n\n

               The baseboards in the hall are in fact painted to look like marble, painted with a feather. The doors are Georgia Heart Pine, painted to look like Mahogany. Both of these effects were recreated to look like what Judge Holt had in the home in the 1850s. The wallpaper pattern is one copied from a pattern from the 1850s as well. The chairs on either side of the Pier mirror were originally at Washington College, known today as Washington and Lee University when General Robert E. Lee served as president of the school in the late 1860s. It has the original gold finish.\n\n

               The clock is known as a “Leaner Clock” because it does not have the back legs. The face was made in Leeds, England, while the base is made out of Mahogany. The entire piece was made before 1820.\n\n

               The back Parlor houses the furniture from the Adelphean Sorority, which was the oldest sorority for women. Founded on May 15, 1851, it would become known as Alpha Delta Pi in the early 1900s when it became a national sorority. The portraits are those of the 6 founders, and the gasolier originally came from the Johnston- Felton- Hay House where it was hung in their formal parlor, or the Reception room. Purchased in the 1920s by a member of ADPi, it was brought to the Cannonball House in the 1960s when the furniture was brought to the home.\n\n

               <b><i>SPOTLIGHT</i></b>- Katie Martin (Roberson), Charles Canning’s granddaughter, was initiated into the Adelphean Sorority at the age of 15.
</item>



        <item>The Pastel on the Landing (as you walk up to the second floor) was done by Miss Lizzie Canning, and it is of Susie Postell Martin, Miss Elizabeth Martin’s mother. Susie would live in the home from 1903 until her death in 1947. In the corner of the pastel is Lizzie’s signature.</item>



        <item>The family portraits over the table were also done by Lizzie Canning. Lizzie entered into Wesleyan College at the age of 16, where she took courses in Art and Drawing. In the late 1880s exhibitions were held on Cotton Ave showing her artwork. Newspaper clippings in her scrapbook declared she was one of the most talented artists in Macon.\n\n

              The table which dates to the 1850s, once was in Susie’s parent’s home on New Street (close to where the Methodist Church has their garden today). It was brought into the Cannonball House around the time Susie married Charles C. Martin.  The Haviland china on the table is original to the family as well.\n\n

              <b><i>SPOTLIGHT</i></b>- The turkey feather fan belonged to Elizabeth Martin, but originally belonged to Judge Holt and his wife. Given to the UDC ladies in the 1960s, most likely it is now over 150 years old.
</item>



        <item>Judge Holt would have used this room as his bedroom when he lived in the home. The wardrobe, which dates to the 1850s, is original to the house. It is made out of mahogany. The dresser is also original to the home. On top of the dresser there is a letter written to Mr. Thomas Hardeman from Alexander H. Stephens. The picture of Fort Hawkins ties into the Cannonball House as well. Judge Holt fought in the War of 1812, and was mustered out of service at Fort Hawkins. He would later build this home where he could look out his bedroom windows and see the Fort across the Ocmulgee River. The shoe shine kit dates to Macon when it was first founded in the 1820s. It even has the original tapestry cover.\n\n

              The bed, made in Louisiana in the 1850s, was purchased by Mr. William Bass, president of Wesleyan College for over 20 years.  The marble topped table at the foot of the bed was used by the Canning family as a spinning game table.\n\n

              The nightstand to the right of the bed is another piece original to the home. Above the nightstand is a portrait of Nora Burke Holt Canning, taken in 1862 when she was 30 years of age around the time she married Judge Holt, when he was 72.\n\n

              <b><i>SPOTLIGHT</i></b>- Miss Elizabeth Martin used this front bedroom as her bedroom/ living area even after she sold the house to the UDC. On many occasions she would have lowered a basket with the front door key inside, so the UDC ladies could enter through the front door. Mr. Tom (the neighbor next door) would bring Miss Elizabeth her gorceries when he was a boy. On those days, Miss Elizabeth would have lowered the basket and key so he could bring the groceries upstairs.
</item>
    </string-array>
</resources>